You weren't followed?
没被跟踪吧？
No.
没
Better come in.
快请进
Trust no one, Jim.
吉姆，谁都别信
Especially not in the mainstream.
尤其是那些要人
Sit down.
请坐
I understand you still have one Hungarian identity running?
我知道你仍有一个匈牙利身份可用
I do.
是的
I want you to go to Budapest.
我想派你去布达佩斯（匈牙利首都）
This is not above board.
秘密行动
Nobody else knows.
他人不知
They're after my head, Jim boy.
他们可是巴不得我失手呢，吉姆小子
Do you understand?
你明白吗？
I have had an offer of service.
我听小道消息说
A Hungarian general wants to come over.
一位匈牙利将军要来访
I would like you to meet him.
我想让你会会他
He has some information that I need, Jim.
他有我要的情报，吉姆
What information?
什么情报？
Treasure.
重要机密
He has the name of the mole,
他知道“鼹鼠”的名字…
the Russians have planted in the British intelligence service
一个俄国佬在英国情报部门安插的内鬼…
right at the top of the Circus.
就在“马戏团”的高层中 (“马戏团”即Cambridge Circus,当时英国情报部门的驻地， 下文提到的“局子”也指此）
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
有个内鬼，吉姆
We have to find it.
我们得把他挖出来
Stop!
站住！
Would you witness this for me?
帮我做个见证吧？
I wish I could done more, Control.
我真希望我当时能多帮点忙，老总。
You did all you could, Percy.
你已经尽力了，珀西
Well, a man should know when to leave the party.
作为男人，须知何时谢幕离场
What about Smiley?
史迈利呢？
Smiley is leaving with me.
史迈利随我一起退休
You little prick, Esterhase.
你个小变态，伊斯特哈斯
Gentlemen, shall we start?
先生们，我们开始吧？
Under Secretary Lacon is ready for you, Sir Percy.
珀西先生，副局长拉康在等您
The Treasury don't understand.
财政部不解
Why can't the intelligence service simply put in a request
情报部门为何不为经费增加的问题
for a general increase in funding
提交一个正式的申请呢
and then you account for the spend on your special operation?
那样不就可以支撑你们的专项行动了吗？
Operation Witchcraft needs to remain secret.
“巫术行动”需要保密
- It's a fiefdom of its own.  - Yes, that's what's worrying us.
- 所以开支由他们自由控制 - 这也是困扰我们的原因
The whole thing's very unaccountable, isn't it?
整件事难以解释，不是吗？
And this London house that nobody knows the address of,
没人知道这间伦敦宅子在哪儿
is that really necessary?
有这个必要吗？
Now more than ever. We need to protect our Soviet source.
比起从前，现在更需要保护 我们苏联情报的来源渠道
So where do you propose we meet? In a caf?
那你认为我们该在哪接头？咖啡馆？
The rent and rates on this house have doubled.
房租和费率都翻了倍
We spent millions on nuclear warheads.
我们在核弹头上花了数百万
We're asking for a few thousand for a house.
却不能为一间房子申请几千块
I wonder if Karla has the same problem
真想知道卡拉是不是也面对着
with the Treasury at the Kremlin.
一样抠门的苏联财政部和克林姆林宫
Look, nobody underestimates
听着，没人低估
the importance of the job you chaps are doing.
你们工作的重要性
But what happened in Budapest last year,
可去年在布达佩斯发生的事
that was a disaster.
着实让人心有余悸
With respect, sir,
恕我直言，先生
it wasn't one of your civil servants that got killed, was it?
牺牲的不是您的手下，对吧？
Now this isn't about soldiers in trenches any more.
军人在战壕里奋战的时代虽然已经过去
- We're the front line now...  - Roy!
- 可我们现在干的和在前线无异… - 罗伊！
For 25 years we've been the only thing
过去的25年里，只有我们在阻止卡拉
and Moscow and the third bloody world war.
莫斯科，以及该死的第三次世界大战
Look, the Minister's very pleased with your progress so far.
听着，部长大人对你们目前工作的进展表示满意
He's less pleased, though,
但是他对你们和我们亲爱的美国表亲之间
with the lack of progress with our American cousins.
缺少协作这点不甚满意
You see,
你知道
in their eyes,
在他们眼中
you're still a leaky ship.
你们还是一艘漏洞百出的破船
Yes?
什么事？
Someone on the line for you, sir. Seems urgent.
有人找您，先生，好像很急
All right, well put him through.
好的，接通吧
- Hello?  - Is this Under Secretary Lacon?
- 你好？ - 是副局长拉康吗？
Yes.
正是
My name's Ricki Tarr.
我叫里基•塔尔
- What do you want?  - I need to meet you.
- 有事吗？ - 我想见您
If you need to confirm who I am,
如果您要核实我的身份，可以找我“马戏团”的上司
Peter Guillam.
彼得•吉勒姆
But only Guillam, no one else.
只有他知道我
You got clearance for that?
允许你骑车进来吗？
Well, I'm not bloody chaining it up outside.
我才不会傻得把它锁在外面呢
Mind you, no better off in here
友情提醒，和里面这些狠角儿放一起相对安全
They'd have the gold out of your teeth.
他们连你嘴里的消息都挖的出来
Thought I'd pop in and catch a glimpse of the new girl
我得赶在布兰德之前看一眼新来的妹子
Ah, yes. Belinda the blonde.
是啊，金发女郎贝琳达
- Has he seen her yet?  - Of course he has.
- 他见过她没？ - 肯定见过
Came down first thing this morning.
今早第一件事就是看她
Belinda.
贝琳达
- Peter Guillam.  - Hello, Peter, this is Oliver.
- 我是彼得•吉勒姆 - 你好啊，彼得，我是奥利弗
Just ringing to find out...
想问问你…
So Winston Churchill saved your life, Edie.
这么说是温斯顿•丘吉尔救了你一命，伊迪
I was working in the kitchen, getting dinner ready.
当时我在厨房备好了晚餐
And he was late, you see.
他迟到了
- During a raid?  - During a raid, you see.
- 突袭的时候？ - 是的
He said, "Why aren't you in that shelter?"
他问，你为什么不在那个避难所？
- Why weren't you?  - Well, because...
- 你不也不在么？ - 因为我…
I was sorry to hear about Control, Mr Smiley.
很遗憾听到老总的死讯，史迈利先生
He said Tarr called him from a phone box.
他说塔尔在电话亭给他致电
He said there's a mole,
他说有“鼹鼠”
right at the top of the Circus,
就在“马戏团”的高层里
that he's been there for years.
已潜伏多年
It does mean
那就是说
you're rather well placed to look into this matter for us now,
你最好给我们立即查清楚原委
doesn't it?
是不？
Outside the family.
把他清除出去
I'm retired, Oliver.
我已经退休了，奥利弗
You fired me.
你解雇了我
The thing is,
实际上
some time ago before Control died,
老总死前
he came to me with a similar suggestion.
曾来找我，暗示我说
That there is a mole.
有“鼹鼠”
He never mentioned his suspicions to you?
他没对你讲过他的怀疑么？
No.
没有
Oh, I just thought that as you were his man, so to speak...
噢，我以为你是他的心腹，会跟你讲…
What did you say to him?
你怎么跟他说的？
I'm afraid I thought his paranoia had rather gotten the better of him
我想恐怕是他的妄想症在作祟
and he was going to pull his whole house down.
再这样下去就要自毁长城了
That bloody mess in Budapest.
还有布达佩斯的惨剧
Damn it, George.
不可否认，乔治
It's your generation, your legacy.
他们可是你孕育的一代，是你留下的财富
I would have thought, if there's any truth in it,
我本以为，要是这事儿听来有几分可信， 你会愿意…
I'll keep Peter.
我要彼得
And there's a retired Special Branch man, Mendel.
还有一个政治保安处退下来的人，孟德尔
I should like to have him.
我要他
Lift up.
提起来
And quickly down again.
再赶紧关好
There's a place I know, sir.
先生，我知道一个利物浦大街附近的小旅馆
Be careful with it. Please. It's Georgian.
请小心点，乔治王时代的
My friend wants peace and quiet in order to work, Mrs Pope Graham.
我朋友想要安静工作，波普·格雷姆夫人
No disturbances.
不要打搅他
Her real name is just Graham.
她真名只是格雷姆
Added the Pope for a touch of class.
加上波普（“教皇”的谐音）以示高贵
Peter, did you get the keys to Control's flat?
彼得，你有老总住处的钥匙吗？
Oh!
噢！
George!
乔治！
George, get in here!
乔治快来
George.
乔治
Sit down.
坐下
Take a look at this nonsense.
看看这些胡言乱语
Report by Soviet high command
苏联最高指挥部的
on their recent naval exercises in the Black Sea.
关于他们近期于黑海的海军演练的报告
Just what the admiralty has been begging us
正是海军部求咱们
for some information on.
弄的情报
- Where did you get this?  - I didn't.
- 哪儿得到的？ - 不是我
Percy and his little cabal walked in with it.
珀西和他的小党羽搞到的
- Look, Control...  - Shut up.
- 听着，老总… - 闭嘴
Style appalling.
文风假得令人无语
Patently a fabrication from beginning to end.
明显从头到尾都是伪造的
Just could be the real thing.
- 也有可能是真的 - 如果是真的，那可价值连城
But its topicality makes it suspect.
不过它到手太快了，令人生疑
Smiley is suspicious, Percy.
史迈利怀疑你了呢，珀西
Where did it come from? What's the access?
哪儿来的？什么渠道？
A new secret source of mine.
我的一个新的秘密线人
But how could he possibly have access?
他怎么可能得到这个的？
He has access to the most sensitive levels of policy-making.
他能参与甚至最机密层级的政策制定
We've named the operation Witchcraft.
我们命名这个行动为“巫术”
Oh, Percy and his pals bypassed us, Smiley.
珀西和他的伙计们真是深谙越俎代庖之术啊，史迈利
Gone straight to the minister.
僭越了我们直接找部长去了
Percy has been allowed to keep the identity of his new friend
珀西那位新朋友，连身份都被
top secret.
钦点为最高机密了呢
The minister agrees too many secrets are blown around here.
部长也认同这里太多的机密被泄露了
Too much failure, too many scandals.
不胜枚举的失败，接连不断的丑闻
Too little solid intelligence.
-有用的情报少得可怜 - 珀西有他的道理，老总
We should be fighting Communism, not each other.
我们应该反共，而不是内讧
Meanwhile we're losing our reputation, our partners.
与此同时，我们信誉扫地，损兵折将
Your bloody Yanks!
你们该死的美国佬！
We've had enough! There's going to be changes.
我们受够了！得改革了
We need to decide if want to be part of the past
是时候决定是固步自封还是开创未来了
I should have left you where I found you.
当年我就不该把你带来
- Look!  - Control...
- 听着！ - 老总…
Out, all of you!
滚，都给我滚出去！
If Witchcraft is genuine...
如果“巫术”是真的…
Nothing is genuine any more.
没有什么是真的
George...
乔治…
Do you want me to get this stuff over to the hotel?
要我把这些东西带到旅馆吗？
Thank you. Er, anywhere will do.
谢谢，随便放
- Peter?  - Hm?
- 彼得？ - 嗯？
I need you to do something for me.
我要你替我办点事
I'd lik e you to go to the Circus.
你去“马戏团”
In the cabinet at the duty officers' station
在值班岗那儿的橱柜里
are records of staff recently retired.
有最近退休人员的记录
I'd like photographs of them
拍成照片给我
and of the diagram of the Circus's reorganisation under Percy Alleline,
还有珀西•阿勒莱恩管理的 “马戏团”发生变动的图表
along with a list of all payments made from the Reptile fund.
和所有行动基金的支付清单
Help you with anything, Bill?
- 比尔，什么事？ - 我在找“陛下”（指珀西）
Well, he's out walking the battlements.
他到天台散步去了
Oh.
哦
Heard you had an accident, Peter.
- 听说你受伤了，彼得？ - 开抽屉的时候夹了手
When are you going to get some new furniture up here?
你什么时候去置办些新家具？
I'll have a word with Esterhase.
我会跟伊斯特哈斯说的，要把这作为决策层的首要大事
- Where are you off to?  - Lunch.
- 你去哪儿？ - 吃午饭
Want some company?
一起？
According to the personnel files,
根据人事档案
seven were due for retirement anyway.
有七个到了退休年龄
Another four don't seem particularly mysterious.
其他四个也没有太明显的疑点
Jerry Westerby was dismissed December 4.
杰瑞•韦斯特比于12月4日被解雇
Connie Sachs retired November 28.
康妮•萨克斯于11月28日退休
That's just two weeks after you and Control were forced out.
那是在你和老总被挤走后的两周里发生的
- Return to Oxford, please.  - That's 1.15.
- 回牛津 - 1点15的车
Percy has always resisted any proposal
珀西向来反对
of a wider exploitation of Witchcraft's intelligence.
广泛利用“巫术”情报的提议
Drop the bloody jargon, Lacon.
别来跟我玩文绉绉的官腔，拉康
I've refused to share Witchcraft with our allies so far, Minister.
我至今未跟同盟们分享过“巫术”，部长大人
Greedy boy.
吝啬的家伙
My goal has been to establish its track record beyond all doubt.
我是想建立一套密不透风的巫术行动情报档案
I think the time has come to approach our American brothers-in-arms.
我觉得是时候携手我们的美国盟友了
Will they take us back into bed?
- 他们会对我们重燃欲火么？ - 我不要一次性交易
I want on-going access to American intelligence.
我要长期的美国情报的分享权
You think we can get it?
你觉得我们能得到吗？
With Witchcraft on our side,
只要有“巫术”，我们可以得到任何想要的
Fine.
好吧
Carry on.
继续下去
Thank you.
谢谢
And I strike thee down...
我要打败你…
Oh, I, er...
哦，我…
Not supposed to. Doctor's orders.
想都别想，医生有吩咐
Wicked, wicked George.
坏坏的乔治
I don't know about you, George,
我不知道你怎么想的，乔治
but I f eel seriously under-fucked.
但我觉得我严重地缺少性爱
I heard Ann left you again.
我听说安又弃你而去了
She doesn't deserve you, George, not one hair on your head.
她配不上你，乔治，连你一根头发都配不上
You left the Circus shortly after I retired.
我退休不久，你也离开了“马戏团”
I didn't leave. I was dismissed.
我是被开除的
Chucked out on the rubbish heap, like you.
被开除的垃圾，和你一样
Why?
为什么？
Polyakov.
波利亚科夫
Do you remember him?
还记得他吗？
From the Soviet Embassy?
苏联大使馆的那位？
Alexsey Polyakov, cultural attache here in London.
阿联克斯•波利亚科夫，以文化交流为由常驻伦敦
When he arrived here 15 years ago, I requested he be checked out.
15年前他来到这里，我要求对其清查
He was graded whiter than white. Didn't put a foot wrong.
可他记录清白，为人谨慎
But you disagreed?
但你不这么认为？
There's a story you must have heard
你肯定听闻过这个传说
that Karla has set up a secret cell.
卡拉设立了个秘密单元
The personnel are all ex-military,
所有成员都是以前军人
trained to handle deep-penetration agents, moles.
训练有素地掌控着资深间谍和“鼹鼠”们
There are always stories, Connie.
传说是不绝于耳的，康妮
But what if this story was true?
万一这个传说是真的呢？
One night in research I saw something, George.
有一晚在调查中我发现了些东西，乔治
There was our friend Polyakov at a May day parade in Berlin
我们的朋友波利亚科夫在柏林五一大阅兵中
receiving a salute.
收到了一个军礼
Why would you salute a cultural attache?
为什么要向一个文化专员敬礼？
Exactly. Unless he was a war veteran himself.
显然，除非他是个退伍军人
And if he was, why hide the fact?
若真如此，为何要隐瞒真相？
What did you do?
你怎么做的？
I went straight to Esterhase and Alleline.
我直接去找托比•伊斯特哈斯和珀西•阿勒莱恩
Here.
看
Polyakov is a Karla-trained hood if ever I saw one.
如果我没弄错的话，波利亚科夫是卡拉训练的人
If he's here, it must be because he's running a mole.
他若在这儿，说明卡拉安插了“鼹鼠”于此
You're to leave Polyakov alone.
你不要管波利亚科夫
You're becoming obsessed with him.
你太纠缠他了
- You're losing your sense of proportion, Connie.  - But that's ridiculous.
- 不要越俎代庖 - 太荒唐了
Perhaps it's time you went out into the real world.
也许是时候让你回到现实的世界了
What does it matter? Old Circus is gone anyway.
走就走，反正从前的“马戏团”已经逝去了
Here we are.
看看这些
The nursery in our day.
我们那时的日子
Jim Prideaux.
吉姆•普里多
And Bill Haydon. Together, of course.
当然还有比尔•海顿 俩人黏在一块，和往常一样
The Inseparables.
“形影不离的一对”
There's Control himself.
还有老总的独照
All my boys.
我的男孩们
All my lovely boys.
我的好战友
That was a good time, George.
那时候多美好啊，乔治
It was the war, Connie.
可那是战争年代啊，康妮
A real war.
那是一场真正的战争
Englishmen could be proud then.
至少那时候英国人还有自豪的理由
So I was right, then?
我还是对的，是吧？
About Polyakov.
至少关于波利亚科夫
There is a mole.
确有“鼹鼠”
If it's bad, don't come back. I want to remember you all as you were.
若真如此，请勿回来 我想把记忆定格在你们都美好的时候
Percy? Percy, did you mix this?
珀西？珀西，你调的这汤？
Aye, I did so.
是，是我调的
You Calvinistic, penny-pinching Scot.
你这个小气的没救的苏格兰人
Can you learn to take a bloody order?
你这种外行就不能按食谱来做吗？
Nobody tampers with the recipe!
谁也不能乱改食谱！
- I followed the recipe.  - Come on.
- 我就是按着食谱来的啊 - 别说了
It'll take us five hours to get drunk on this monkey's piss.
这猴尿大家喝五个小时也喝不醉啊
- # He's the second best secret agent #  - Merry Christmas.
圣诞快乐
- Courtesy of Mrs P.  - Hm?
- 皮夫人问好 - 嗯？
You been up all night?
你通宵了？
Yes.
是的
What's this?
这是什么？
Request for $1,000 in cash from the Reptile fund.
去行动基金要的1000英镑现金
To a Mr Ellis.
给一个叫埃尔斯的先生
It was one of Jim Prideaux's work names.
吉姆•普里多的一个工作化名
Prideaux was killed in Hungary a year ago.
普里多一年前于匈牙利遇害
October 21.
10月21日
So why was someone giving him $1,000 two months later?
那为何还有人于两个月后给他1000英镑？
I wonder where he is then, sir.
那我不禁要想他到底现在在哪儿呢？
Settle down now.
安静
- Hand those out.  - Sir.
- 发下去 - 是，先生
What is it? The Hunchback of Notre-Dame?
这是什么？巴黎圣母院的敲钟人？
The bells, the bells!
钟，钟！
Ohh!
噢！
Come here.
出来吧
- What's your name?  - Roach. Bill Roach, sir.
- 叫什么名字？ - 罗奇，比尔•罗奇
- I'm a new boy.  - New arrival, eh?
- 我是新生 - 新来的哦？
- What's the story?  - My mother and father.
- 怎么回事？ - 我父亲和母亲
My father left, so...
我父亲离开了，所以…
Hm.
嗯
Bill.
比尔（账单）
The unpaid Bill.
未付账的账单
- Anyone ever call you that?  - No, sir.
- 有人那么叫你吗？ - 没有，先生
Known a lot of Bills in my time.
我认识很多叫比尔的人
They've all been good 'uns.
他们都是好人
What are you good at?
你擅长什么？
Nothing, sir.
一无所长，先生
You're a good watcher, though, eh?
但你擅于观察，对吗？
Us loners always are.
我们孤独者都如此
Best watcher in the unit, Bill Roach is, I'II bet.
一旦你带上眼镜，我打赌，比尔•罗奇
- Long as he's got his specs on. Right?  - Yes, sir.
- 你一定是班上最好的观察者，对吗？ - 是的，先生
This is good, very good.
很好，非常好
Hello, Ricki.
你好，里基
You've missed the wedge.
你疏忽了门上的楔子
Where have you been, Ricki?
你去哪了，里基？
They're going to kill me.
他们追杀我
- Who is?  - Your lot.
- 谁？ - 你们的人
Or their lot. Whoever gets me first.
或许是他们的人，无论谁逮到，我都得死
I'm innocent.
我是清白的
Within reason.
我有我的理由
How long have you been here?
你来这多久了？
Sorry, I've run out of places now.
对不起，我走投无路
I needed to see you.
我需要见你
Why?
为什么？
There's a woman.
有一个女人
I need you to trade for her. I need you to get her back off Karla.
我需要你去交易帮我把她从卡拉那弄回来
A woman?
什么女人？
Her name's Irina.
她叫依瑞娜
This was last November.
去年十一月
Mr Guillam sent me to Istanbul to check out a Russian trade delegate
吉勒姆先生派我去伊斯坦布尔调查一个俄贸代表
who might be persuaded to defect.
这人有被说服投靠我方的可能
- Tufty Thesinger, resident.  - Yeah.
- 叫塔夫帝•赛森哲，驻外政治代表 - 就是他
- Hiya, Ricki.  - All right, mate?
- 你好，里基 - 旅程还行吧，伙计？
- Did you know him?  -No, never met him.
- 你认识他？ - 不，没见过
Bit of a drinker.
那人有点嗜酒
Hangover from hell.
宿醉的鬼样
Bit of a fucking idiot.
挺白痴的
Apparently this Russian, name of Boris,
很明显这个叫鲍里斯的俄国人
was spending high and wide in the nightclubs.
混迹于各个夜店，浪荡挥霍
So you were sent to persuade this Boris?
你就是来游说这个鲍里斯的？
Yeah. He was your typical Russian.
是的，他就是典型的俄国人
Trade delegation by day, out boozing every night.
天亮贸易谈判，夜晚寻欢作乐
Didn't seem to sleep.
乐此不疲
Tufty was worn out from following him around.'
这可把跟踪他的塔夫帝给熬倒了
I think it's going to be a long night, son.
漫漫长夜啊，孩子
His favourite haunt was this club in Taksim.
他常出没于塔克西姆广场的一个夜总会
It had a hellhole in the basement where the sailors and the tourists went.
地下室有个“天上人间”，水手和游客常常光顾
Anyway, I took one look at him and I knew I'd wasted a journey.
总之，我看他一眼，就觉得我这趟白跑了。
Boris was no delegate.
鲍里斯不是什么代表
What delegate bothers to play drunker than he really is?
有哪个代表会醉成这样？除非是装的
You get to recognise your own, don't you, Mr Smiley?
我们得学会认出同行，是不是，史迈利先生？
And Boris was a hood
鲍里斯是莫斯科“中心”
Moscow Centre trained.
训练出来的间谍
I guessed he was waiting for a connect.
我猜他在等接头
Working a letterbox, maybe.
也可能在搞一个微缩胶卷
Or trailing his coat and looking for a pass from some mug like me.'
或者拖着他的大衣，在人群中找一个像我这样的人给他信号
So the second night I went to the import/export outfit
所以次夜我去了趟进出口机构
that Tufty had set up with a cipher room hidden in the back.
塔夫帝在深处设了间密室
I cabled "No sale" to Mr Guillam.
我发送了“不外售”的电报给吉勒姆先生
And that was that.
就那样
You were due to fly home the next day.
次日你本该飞回来
Yes.
是的
But you didn't.
但你没有
Boris had a wife.
鲍里斯有一个老婆
Common-law.
法律上的妻子
Apparently she was a member of the delegation in her own right.
显然她也是有一席之地的代表团成员
You once told me to trust my instincts about women, Mr Smiley.
史迈利先生，您曾教导我相信对女人的直觉
Well, my instincts told me this woman had some treasure.
我的直觉告诉我，这个女人有料
When Boris went out for the night, I found myself going into her hotel.'
那晚当鲍里斯出去后，我告诉自己该去旅馆找她
So you dropped Boris.
所以你放弃跟踪鲍里斯
I know. It was breaking protocol.
我知道我坏了规矩
But I was acting on my own initiative, as it were.
但可以说是我不由自主地在行动
Your man's a bit of a bastard, isn't he?
你男人真混蛋，不是吗？
I just wanted to make sure you were all right, OK?
我只是想看看你有没有事，好吗？
So you didn't come home?
所以你没有回来？
I would have.
本该回的
Boris was a dead end, but...
最后鲍里斯那条路是个死胡同，可是…
Um...
唔…
I could...
我可以…
I could sense something in her.
我可以在她身上感觉到某种东西
A secret.
她有秘密
And how did you intend to get this secret out of her?
那你打算怎么从她那弄到这个秘密？
I played this businessman, Michael Trench.
我装成一个叫迈克尔•钱奇的商人
Holiday romance.
共度浪漫假日
I thought I'd take my time with it.
我心想不着急
I know who you are.
我知道你的真实身份
I want to talk to your boss.
我要跟你的上司谈话
Control.
老总
I have something to trade.
我有东西要交易
Something big.
很重要
I want a new life in the West.
我想在西方重新生活
That's the deal.
这就是我的要求
You tell them.
你转告他们
Look, you can't expect them to jump at every offer of service.
听着，别指望他们对任何情报都欣然接受
If you won't tell me more, there is nothing I can do.
如果你不能提供更多的情报，我也无能为力
If I tell you everything,
若我全盘托出
I'm putting my life in your hands.
那我就把命交到你的手里了
And the lives of other people.
还有其他人的命
So she told me what she had to trade.
于是她就告诉了我她要交换的
Her secret.
秘密
I mean,
我意思是
the mother of all secrets.
所有秘密的源头
I told her I'd alert the Circus.
我告诉她我会通知“马戏团”的
She made me promise I wouldn't give any of the details to London.
她要我保证不能向伦敦透露任何细节
- And you agreed?  - Yes.
- 你同意了 - 是的
I mean it was...
我意思…
I couldn't believe I'd got hold of something this big.
我都不敢相信我搞到了这么大的情报
I went back to the import export,
我回到进出口机构
sent the message to the Circus, graded, "Flash, highest priority",
给“马戏团”发了封“最高紧急级别”的电报
just that I had a Moscow-trained hood wanting to defect.
说我有一个想叛变的莫斯科同行
You're supposed to have gone. London stations have been on to me.
你怎么还没走，伦敦当局找上我了
Want to know what the hell you're doing.
想知道你到底在搞什么鬼
Fuck off.
滚开
Anything else, Ricki?
还有吗，里基？
I know what I am to the Circus. I'm one of the scalp-hunters,
我知道对于“马戏团”，我只是一名头皮猎人
someone that you can hand your dirty little jobs to.
那些下作肮脏的任务都可以扔给我干
I just...
我只是…
I just wanted to bring this one in myself.
我只是想把这件事摊给自己而已
Well, I understand how you felt.
我理解你的感受
You wanted to do something.
你想有所成就
Vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
重要情报
Anything more?
还有吗？
I said that she had information concerning a double agent.
我还说她的情报事关一个双面间谍…
Look, I just wanted to get the proper attention. And I'd...
听着，我只想引起足够的重视，而且…
I told them this was the reason why I had not come home.
我告诉他们这就是我当时没有回来的原因
It wasn't that I'd defected or anything.
并不是我叛变了什么的
- What did you do then?  - I waited for a reply.
- 你之后怎么做的？ - 我等待回复
I hung around for hours. I remember heard the lmsak call to prayer.
我来回走了几个小时，还听到了穆斯林的祈祷昭告
- So what's that time?  - That's about 3. 30 in the morning.'
之后，凌晨3点半左右吧
Then the message comes through.
电报来了
"We read you."
“知道了”
That was all they sent. Nothing.
仅此，别无他言
It didn't make sense. It was like they were stalling.
讲不通啊，他们就像在拖延时间
Then what happened?
然后呢？
Then, all of a sudden...
突然…
the Russians begin to move.
俄国佬开始行动了
It was nice work. I couldn't have done it better myself.
手法漂亮，就像我亲自下手的一样
The message was quite clear. I needed to warn her. '
这信息很明了，我得警告她
Come on, come on, come on.
快点，快点
I looked for her everywhere couldn't find her at the airport.
我在机场找不到她
I even looked through all the flight lists and...
我几乎查看了所有的班次…
I headed down to the harbour.
还去了港口
They put her on a ship to Odessa.
他们把她押到了去敖德萨(乌克兰港市)的船上
That's all I know.
我只知道这么多
I've...
我…
I've done a lot of things in my life, Mr Smiley, but...
我此生做了很多事情，史迈利先生，可…
I just... I can't stop thinking about her.
她却让我难以忘怀
She wasn't even my type.
她甚至不是我喜欢的类型
I've got to get her out. I owe her that.
我得把她弄出来，我欠她的
Karla will be looking for you.
卡拉会找你的
Everybody's looking for me.
人人都在找我
You can't stay here.
此地不宜久留
It isn't safe.
不安全
OK. Just need to let you know.
好了，只是想让你知道
Someone flew into Paris last week on one of our escaped passports.
有人上周飞达巴黎了， 是我们的人，逃过了护照检查
- And?  - lt wasRicki Tarr.
- 然后呢？ - 此人就是里基•塔尔
Why are you telling me?
你告诉我这个干什么？
- It could be coincidence...  - You are a poisoned dwarf.
- 可能是巧合吧… - 你这个脑残死矮子
Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty?
你为何不滚回你的陛下那儿去？
and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret
别指望我成为你滑稽秀的一员
Mr Esterhase: "It could be coincidence,but..."
伊斯特哈斯先生说：“可能是巧合吧…”
Mr Haydon interrupting.
海顿先生打断说
You really are a poisoned dwarf, Toby.
“你这个脑残死矮子”
Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
你为何不滚回你的陛下（指珀西）那儿去？
and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret?
别指望我成为你滑稽秀的一员
You look tired.
你看起来很疲惫
I didn't sleep well.
没睡好
You're going to do something for me, Peter.
彼得，为我做点事
I need the duty officer's log book for last November.
我需要去年11月值班处的登记日志
I'm going to have to send you up a floor into the lions' den.
我不得不更进一步送你去虎穴
If you're caught, you can't mention me.
你若被逮
I'm sorry, but you're alone.
很抱歉，可是你只能靠自己
- Last November?  - Hm.
- 去年11月的？ - 嗯
Mr Guillam!
吉勒姆先生！
Thank you, Bryant.
谢谢你，布莱恩特
How's the family?
家人还好吧？
Fine. Need to go up to the registry today.
挺好的，我今天要上登记处去
OK, sir.
好的
Now you'll need a yellow one for the bag, sir.
那你得为你的箱子拿个黄色权限，先生
Thank you.
谢谢
- Good morning, Mr Guillam.  - Morning, Alwyn.
- 早安，吉勒姆先生 - 早，阿尔文
- Want me to look after that for you?  - Thank you.
- 需要我帮您保管吗？ - 谢谢
I'll need your chit, Mr Guillam.
我得看看您的权限，吉勒姆先生
Dolphin will kill me if I don't. New rules.
上头要是知道我省了这步程序非杀了我不可， 这是新规定
So, chit me.
请便
Thanks.
谢谢
- So lovely surprise.  - Peter.
- 桑儿，很高兴见到你 - 彼得
- What are you up to this weekend?  - Oh, you know.
- 周末做什么去？ - 你知道的
Visiting aunts.
拜访七大姑八大姨
I'll bet.
我猜就是
Corridor D.
D走廊
The two eights are halfway on your right.
中途右侧88号
The three ones are next alcove down.
111号在下一个凹室
Thanks.
多谢
Hello. Archive, Alwyn speaking.
你好，档案部，我是阿尔文，请讲
Can I speak to Mr Guillam, please? '
我找吉勒姆
I'm his car mechanic.
我是他的修车工
Well, I'll just see if he's available. Hold on, please.
我去看看他是否有空，请稍等
- Oh, Christ!  - Telephone, sir.
- 天哪！ - 有你电话，先生
- Who is it? - Outside line, sir. Someone rough.
- 什么人？ - 外线，一个大老粗
Sir?
先生？
- Hello?  - Your gearbox is bust, sir.
- 喂？ - 您的变速箱崩了，先生
Damn it, can't you fix the bloody thing?
该死，你难道不会修吗？
Can't be done. Probably you need a new gear box, sir.
不好修
Well, phone the main dealership first. Have you got their number?
给经销商打电话好不，你有他们电话吗？
No.
没有
Hang on. Alwyn!
等下，阿尔文！
- Alwyn.  - Sir?
- 阿尔文 - 什么事？
Get me my bag, will you?
把我的包给我，可以吗？
- But...  - Just for a second.
- 可… - 就一下
Thank you.
谢谢
Hang on.
等下
- Hello?  - I'm listening.
- 在吗？ - 我在听
- Yes. 9-4-6-0-3-3-5.  - Be right on it, sir.
- 记住了，先生
Thank you.
谢谢
Peter Guillam.
彼得•吉勒姆
Could we see you, please?
能跟我们见个面吗？
Percy would like quite an urgent word with you.
珀西有些紧急的话要跟你说
If you can come now to the fifth floor that would be so kind.
如果你现在能去趟五楼，就最好不过了
Yes, of course.
好的
Throw that into the lift for me.
替我把这扔到升降机里去
Send it to the second floor, save me filling out bloody chits.
送到三楼，省的我去填那些烦人的单子
Will do, sir.
放心，先生
So what have you been getting up to down there these days?
你最近都在忙些什么呢？
Apart from chasing our virgins.
除了调戏我们的黄花大闺女们？
A couple of Arab ploys that look quite promising.
一些在阿拉伯的行动看上去会有些斩获
Apart from that, I'm getting quite good at ping-pong.
除此之外，我在乒乓球上大为精进
Arabs.
阿拉伯人
You can rent one but you can't buy one. Right, Bill?
你可以租借他们，但无法收买他们,对吧，比尔？
How's Ricki Tarr these days?
里基•塔尔近来如何？
Fine. We have tea at Fortnum's every afternoon.
挺好的，我们每天在福特纳姆喝下午茶
I require the matter of your discussion with Tarr.
我想知道你与塔尔谈话的内容
I'll tell him. He'll be thrilled.
我会转告他的，他会很兴奋的
What's that shrug for?
你耸什么肩？
I'm talking to you about the traitor
我在跟你谈论一个叛徒
who cut the throat of our man in Istanbul.
他在伊斯坦布尔把我们的人割喉了
I'm talking to you about a defector from your own damn section.
我在讲一个反水的，而他是该死的你的手下
I'm accusing you of consorting with an enemy agent behind my back.
我控告你，背着我，与一名敌方特工勾结
Don't damn well shrug at me!
所以别他妈的对我耸肩
How would you like a term in prison?
要不你去监狱呆上一会？
Well, I haven't been seeing him.
好吧，我没有见过他
So get your facts straight and get off my back!
你能老实点别随便咬人么？
So... if I told you Tarr had recently arrived in Paris,
那么…我若告诉你塔尔最近到巴黎了
would you be surprised?
你会吃惊么？
No, nothing would surprise me about Ricki Tarr.
不会的，里基•塔尔的任何动作都不会令我惊讶
And if I told you we happen to know 30,000 mysteriously appeared
那我若告诉你我们偶然发现他的银行账户
in his bank account last month,
多了30000英镑来路不明的钱
would that surprise you?
你会惊讶吗？
Your man's a defector, Guillam.
你手下是个叛徒，吉勒姆
Turned by the opposition months ago
被敌方几个月前收买，如今人家把他派回来了
- What for?  - Never mind what for.
- 为什么？ - 这不重要
To muddy the water, that's what for.
就是要弄得我们鸡犬不宁
To spread a whole lot of damn nonsense to get us chasing our tails.
散步大量假情报让我们自乱阵脚
The point is this.
关键是
He's heading for home.
他要回英国
The first peep from him, you come to the grown-ups.
你看到他的第一眼，就立刻来爸爸们这儿报告
Understood?
明白？
Anyone you see around this table but not another damn soul.
除了在坐的，谁都不许告诉
Get out.
出去
Peter?
彼得？
Thank you, Belinda.
谢谢你，贝琳达
All go smoothly, did it?
还顺利吧？
I need to go to the hotel to see George.
我得去旅馆见乔治
Mr Smiley isn't at the hotel, sir. Change of venue.
史迈利先生不在旅馆，换地方了
George?
乔治？
Mr Guillam...
吉勒姆先生…
Sorry it took me so long to come home.
很抱歉耽搁那么久才回来
Ricki has been helping us, Peter.
里基一直在帮我们，彼得
He's been telling us all about his adventures.
他告诉了我们他的所有经历
He's a double, George.
他是双重间谍，乔治
There is no mole. Whole thing's been thought up by Moscow.
根本没有“鼹鼠”，整个事件都是俄国人一手策划的
Karla bought him for 30,000.
卡拉用30000块收买他
I stole that because of you.
为了你我去偷那些文件
I spied on my own because of him.
我亲自做间谍都是因为他，你知道我的感受吗？
Ricki...
里基…
you said you sent the Circus a telegram
你说给“马戏团”发电报，提及依瑞娜的情报
- That's right.  - What was the date?
- 没错 - 什么时候？
He doesn't know because there was no telegram.
他不知道，因为就没发
- The whole thing is a fabrication.  - 20th November.
- 整个事情都是他杜撰的 - 11月20日
It must have been 20th November. Evening.
我清楚的记得是11月20日，晚
lrina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
高层的每个人都笑得肚子痛
- She told me Karla...  - November 20th is missing.
- 她告诉我卡拉… - 11月20日…没有了
Someone is covering their tracks, unless of course you think
有人销毁了记录，除非你觉得
that's just a coincidence?
这是巧合？
What about the money?
那么钱呢？
30,000 isn't so much for Karla to pay if it protects his mole.
用30000块来保护他的“鼹鼠”，对卡拉来说不算多
I'm afraid someone in the Circus knows all about Mr Tarr
恐怕“马戏团”里有人对塔尔了如指掌
and is doing everything they can to discredit him.
尽其所能去栽赃给他
Everything the Circus thinks its' gold is shit, made in Moscow.
“马戏团”自认为重要的情报不过是俄国“中心”制造的垃圾
Why didn't you tell me that you had Tarr?
你为什么不告诉我你窝藏了塔尔？
In case I never made it out of the Circus.I should get some rest.
...是怕我入了虎穴再也回不来了
I suppose you've got your reading to do.
估摸着你也有些阅读工作要做
Come up.
跟我来
I met him once.
我见过他一次
Karla.
卡拉
In 55.
在1955年
Moscow Centre was in pieces.
俄国的“中心”支离破碎
Purge after purge.
一个接一个的清洗
Half their agents were jumping ship.
他们半数的间谍都叛逃了
I travelled around, signing them up.
我四处奔走，把他们拉入阵营
Hundreds of them.
好几百号人
One of them was calling himself Gerstmann.
有一个自称是格斯特曼的人
He was on his way back to Russia
他准备回俄国
and we were pretty sure he was going to be executed.
而我们当时也很确信他回去会被处决
Plane had a 24-hour lay-over at Delhi and that's how long I had
飞机要在德里停24小时，我要用那仅有的一天
to convince him to come over to us
说服他投靠我们
instead of going home to die.
别傻乎乎的回国去死
There's a little room.
在那个小屋子
I'm sitting here. He's sitting there.
我坐这儿，他坐那儿
The Americans had him tortured.
美国佬对他严刑逼供过
He had no fingernails.
他连指甲都没了
It's incredibly hot.
当时无比炎热
I'm very tired and all I want to do is get this over with and get back home.
我很累，只想快点结束，然后回家
Things weren't going well with Ann.
又跟安闹别扭
I give him the usual pitch.
我对他来老的那一套
"Come to the West and we can give you a comfortable life,
“来西方吧，告诉我们你知道的
"after questioning."
“然后我们给你安稳的生活”
What did he say?
他怎么回答？
"Think of your wife.
“想想你的妻子
You have a wife, don't you?
“你有妻子，对吧？
Here. I brought you some cigarettes, by the way.
“我给你带了点烟
Use my lighter.
“用我的打火机
We could arrange for her to join you. We have a lot of stock to trade.
“我们能安排她也过来，我们手上有很多交换筹码
If you go back, she'll be ostracised. Think of her."
“如果你回去，她会被流放的，想想她
"Think about..."
“想想吧”…
I kept on...
我一直…
harping on about the damn wife,
喋喋不休地说他的妻子
telling him more about me than...
把自己的很多事也告诉他…
I should have walked out, of course.
我本该走掉
But for some reason it seemed important to save this one, so I go on.
但冥冥之中觉得救他很重要，所以我继续
"We're not so very different you and I.
“你我并非千差万别
We've both spent our lives
“我们都竭尽一生
looking for the weaknesses in one another's systems."
“想要找出彼此制度上的缺陷
"Don't you think it's time to recognise
“你不觉得现在你该承认
there is as little worth on your side as there is on mine?"
“你和我都一样的毫无价值吗？”
Never said a word.
他什么都没说
Not one word.
一个字都没说
And the next morning he got back on his plane.
次日早晨他回到飞机上
He handed the pack of cigarettes back to me, untouched.
他还给我那包烟，没动过
This was a chain-smoker, you may mind.
他本是个“烟鬼”，却一根没吸
And he flew off to what he presumed would be his death.
他毅然决然地飞向了预想中的死亡
He kept my lighter.
他保留了我的打火机
It was a gift.
就当是个礼物吧
"To George from Ann.
“安赠予乔治
All my love."
“倾吾所爱”
That was Karla.
他就是卡拉
He went back to die rather than giving in.
他宁愿死也不愿放弃
Yes, and that's how I know he can be beaten.
而正是如此，我知道他并非无懈可击
Because he's a fanatic.
因为他是个疯狂的信徒
And the fanatic is always concealing a secret doubt.
而这些信徒们永远都藏有一个秘密的困惑
What did he look like?
他长什么样？
I can't remember.
记不得了
After today, Peter,
从今天起，彼得
you have to assume they're watching you.
你必须意识到他们会监视你
If there's anything you need tidied up,
若有什么该清理的东西
now is the time.
赶紧清理
Nearly done.
快完成了
For God's sake.
哦上帝啊
Sometimes I think they're all sharing the same moronic brain.
有时我觉得他们都一样的白痴
If there's someone else, you can tell me.
如果你有新欢了，你可以告诉我
I'm a grown-up.
我是大人了
I know. It's just going to be such a wonderful Christmas.
我知道，这将是个美好的圣诞节
Excuse me.
抱歉
Peter, when you're ready
彼得，准备好了
Put it on now.
开始播放
Everybody!
大家一起！
- Jerry. - George.
- 杰瑞 - 乔治
- Peter. - Jerry.
- 彼得 - 杰瑞
I need to talk to you.
我得跟你谈谈
About the night Jim Prideaux was killed.
关于吉姆•普里多遇害的那晚
You were duty officer, weren't you?
那晚你值班，对吗？
Yeah. Control asked me to mind the phones that night.
是的，那晚老总让我守着电话
He said someone was doing a special job for the service.
他说有人在执行一项特别任务
He wanted someone he could trust.
他要自己信得过的人坐镇
There's been a bit of a panic, sir.
出事了，长官
This is from the FO resident clerk.
这是从外交部过来的消息
A Hungarian news bulletin.
一则匈牙利简要新闻
"British spy, work name Ellis,
“化名为埃利斯的英国间谍
travelling with false Hungarian papers,
“利用假护照潜入匈牙利
has attempted to kidnap an unnamed Hungarian General in Budapest.
“计划在布达佩斯绑架一名不愿意透露姓名的匈牙利将军
He's been shot.
“据悉，此人已被击毙
Other arrests imminent."
“相关逮捕行动已经展开”
Can I have a brief, please?
要我做个简报么？
Sir? Do you want me to deny it, sir?
长官，您希望我发布否认声明吗？
I couldn't get a word out of Control.
老总一个字也不跟我说
So I followed protocol and went for the emergency list.
我只能按照程序查询了紧急事务的处理方法
You rang my house.
你打到我家了
Just on the off-chance you were back from Berlin.
碰碰运气看您是否从柏林回来了
What did you say?
你说什么了？
- Hello? - Hello, Mrs Smiley.
- 你好？ - 你好，史迈利夫人
It's Jerry. Jerry Westerby from the office.
我是杰瑞，局里的杰瑞•韦斯特比
Just that there'd been a bit of a crisis.
出点小状况
Ann said you wasn't back yet and that was it.
安说你尚未回来
Go on.
然后呢
All hell broke loose.
都乱套了
Military yelling about Hungarian tanks on the border.
军方说匈牙利的坦克已经在边界上了
Lacon and the minister baying at the door.
老总和部长开始着急了
Thank Christ Bill Haydon turned up when he did.
谢天谢地比尔•海顿在关键时刻出现了
- Mr. Haydon.  - Not now.
- 海顿先生 - 现在不行！
Mr. Haydon!
海顿先生！
Out!
出去！
- Tell me. - I tried to get hold of you.
- 告诉我发生了什么 - 我试着找过你
I got half a story on the ticker tape at my club. Tell me.
我已经从俱乐部的电报上得知大略了，告诉我
Jim Prideaux's been shot.
吉姆•普里多中枪了
Get me the Hungarian embassy.
接通匈牙利大使馆
You go and tell your masters what will happen
你转告你的上司们若敢动吉姆•普里多一根毫毛
if one hair on Jim Prideaux's head is damaged.
后果自负
Get Esterhase on the phone. Tell him to call in the Hungarian agents.
让伊斯特哈斯接电话，让他召回我们在匈牙利所有的特工
Yes, sir.
好的，先生
Any more news on him? Sir?
有普里多的新消息吗？先生？
Oh, God.
天哪
We need to get down to his flat, clear out anything linked.
赶紧去他的住处，清除所有相关的东西
Haydon heard the news at his club?
海顿在他的俱乐部听到了消息？
It's arguable.
在萨维尔俱乐部
At 1: 30? The ticker-tape wouldn't have been running.
凌晨1：30？那么晚电报肯定下班了
So how did he know?
那他是怎么知道的？
- Jesus, George.  - Peter!
- 天啊，乔治 - 彼得！
- Jesus Christ! How could he have known?  - It's not what you think.
- 他怎么知道的？ - 不是你所想的
- Then how did he know?  - Because he was at my house that night.
- 那他是怎么知道的？ - 那晚他在我家
Good flight?
旅途还行吧？
Yes.
还行
Pleasant enough.
挺好的
I was just passing. I thought I'd call in.
我路过，心想拜访一下
Ann was in bed. She insisted on getting up.
安还在睡，但坚持要起来
She said she'd be down in a minute.
她说她一会儿下来
That's what I'm dropping off. It's an awful daub really.
我带来的，其实是个很烂的涂鸦
But Ann expressed a liking.
不过安说喜欢
What's keeping her?
她喜欢哪一点？
Keep going.
继续
Come on, lads. Keep up.
快点，小伙子们，跟上
Come on, Bill!
快点，比尔！
- Got your specs on, Jumbo?  - Yes, sir.
- 戴上眼镜，胖子？ - 是，先生
Come here.
过来
Who's that fellow down there?
你看那是谁？
I don't know, sir.
我不认识
Who is he?
他是谁？
Beggar man?
乞丐？
Thief?
小偷？
Why doesn't he look this way, hm?
为什么他不看这边，嗯？
Wouldn't you if you saw a bunch of boys flogging a car round a field?
换做是你，肯定会朝这群追着车嬉戏的孩子看的
What's the matter with him? Doesn't he like us?
他怎么回事？讨厌我们？
I don't hold with odd-bods hanging around.
我不喜欢奇怪的家伙在旁边
He might steal the Alvis.
他可能要偷阿尔维斯？
- Which is?  - The best car in England, sir.
- 阿尔维斯是什么？ - 英国最好的车，先生
Good lad.
好小伙
How were you briefed for the Budapest mission?
你怎么领到布达佩斯任务的？
Control asked me to come to a flat in Kensington.
老总让我去肯辛顿（伦敦地名）的一处公寓
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
有个内鬼，吉姆
And we have to find it.
我们得找出来
What did you make of it, Jim?
你是怎么理解的，吉姆？
Control's theory?
老总的说法？
I thought it was madness.
我觉得有点疯狂
I know that it is one of five men.
我知道是五人之一
All I want from you is one code name.
你只用告诉我他们的代号
Alleline. Tinker.
阿勒莱恩
Haydon. Tailor.
海顿
Bland. Soldier.
布兰德
We drop Sailor. It's too close to Tailor.
我们不用“水手”，读音太接近“裁缝”了
And Rich Man doesn't seem to be applicable.
“阔佬”又不太合适
Esterhase. Poor Man.
伊斯特哈斯
And the fifth?
第五个呢？
Smiley.
史迈利
I thought it was madness.
我觉得太荒唐了
To think that any one of you could have been a traitor.
认为你们五人中有一个是叛徒
Absolute madness.
这不是疯了是什么
But you still went.
但你还是去了
Why?
为什么？
I went because Control asked me to go.
我去是因为老总之言
It's called doing one's duty.
这叫尽职
At the station I met the legman who was supposed to take me to the General.
在车站我遇到了可以带我去见将军的人
The waiter must have panicked.
侍者一定是慌了
It was meant to be a simple snatch job.
原本是个简单的任务
They drove me to some military hospital,
他们把我带到一个部队医院
and then put me on a transport plane.
然后把我运上运输机
I could tell by the stars we were heading east.
从星星来判断，我们在往东飞
Then they worked me for...
然后他们拷问我…
I don't know how long.
我不知道拷问了多久
Weeks, maybe months.
几周或者几个月
What did you tell them?
你跟他们说什么了？
Everything.
所有的
I held on for as long as I could to let everyone get the hell out of there.
我尽可能地坚持，让其他人有时间撤离
Did they?
他们逃走了吗？
My network s in Hungary, did they get out?
我的匈牙利同伴们得救了吗？
No, they were blown.
没有，他们全栽了
The story is you blew them to save your own skin.
传闻说你为了免受皮肉之苦而告发了他们
After the interrogators had cleared out, this little fellow turned up.
当拷问者都走了以后，有个矮个子男人出现了
Looked like a priest.
像个神父
That's when they really started on me.
对我的逼供才真正开始
What was your last line of defence, hmm?
你的最后防线是什么？
The mole.
“鼹鼠”
Control's crazy theory.
老总疯狂的想法
I was going to bury that so deep they'd never get it out of me.
我将它藏在内心最深处，他们挖不出来
- Which was a joke.  - Why?
- 结果却是个笑话 - 为什么？
Because they already knew.
因为他们早就知道了
All they wanted to know was how far Control had got in his investigation.
他们只是想看看老总到底挖了多深
Did they ask about me at all?
他们没有问起我吗？
Yes.
问过
The little fellow did.
矮个子男人问过
What did he say about me?
他怎么问的？
He had this cigarette lighter.
他有一个打火机
He kept flashing it about for me to see it.
他拿着打火机在我面前不停地晃
Showed me the inscription.
给我看上面的字
- "To George..."  - "... from Ann."
- “安赠予”… - “乔治”
"All my love."
“倾吾所爱”
Karla.
是卡拉
It was odd.
太奇怪了
They sent me back to England.
他们把我送回英国
Straight to Sarratt for debriefing.
直接到Sarratt（英国南部的一个小村庄）汇报情况
He said when he was being debriefed at the nursery, he had a visitor.
他说在医院汇报情况的期间还有一位来访者
Who?
谁？
Toby Esterhase.
托比•伊斯特哈斯
He gave him 1,000 and an Alvis.
他给了他1000块和一辆阿尔维斯
Told him he was dead now. Couldn't come back.
并告诉他他现在身份上已经死了，永勿回来
Had to become a lotus eater, forget everything that happened.
去过安逸的生活，忘掉发生的一切
Control's theory.
忘掉老总的事情
Tinker, Tailor. All of it.
忘掉锅匠，裁缝等
Yes, that's what I thought.
我在想
How on earth did Esterhase hear about Tinker, Tailor?
托比•伊斯特哈斯是怎么得知锅匠、裁缝这档子事的？
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
She told me Karla was very proud of this.
她说卡拉为此颇为自豪
She said everything the Circus thinks is gold is shit, made in Moscow.
她说，“马戏团”自认为重要的情报 不过是莫斯科“中心”炮制的垃圾
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
No, I had a hotel nearby. They do have some seedy rooms.
不，附近有家旅馆，他们有几间闲置室
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
She told me Karla was very proud of this...
她说卡拉以此为乐
She said everything the Circus thinks is gold is shit.
她说，“马戏团”自认为重要的情报 不过是莫斯科“中心”炮制的垃圾
This meeting is not taking place. Is that clear?
这次会面从来都没有发生过，明白吗？
Perfectly, Minister.
明白，部长大人
There is a house somewhere in this city
这城市里有栋房子
where Alleline and the others meet Witchcraft's London representative.
阿勒莱恩等人在那里跟“巫术”的伦敦代表碰头
I thought Lacon had made it clear to you.
我想拉康跟你说得很明了了
Keep your nose bloody well out of Witchcraft's business.
不要插手“巫术”的事
It's Lacon's advice I'm following.
我听从的是拉康的建议啊
You told me to follow in Control's footsteps.
你让我紧跟老总的脚步的
I wouldn't consider that sound advice, given the mess Control left us with.
想想老总给我们留下的烂摊子， 我不觉得这是个好建议
It has taken Alleline and, if I may say so, myself
花了阿勒莱恩，以及，并非自夸，我本人
this long to get us back in the game.
那么久才使“马戏团”重回正轨
The man Alleline and the others meet is called Polyakov.
阿勒莱恩等人会见的那人叫波利亚科夫
You believe his role is to bring information from Witchcraft to you.
从“巫术”带情报给你
His real role is to receive information from the mole
其实他真正的任务是从“鼹鼠”那里接收情报
to take back to Karla.
然后带回给卡拉
That, er... that's not possible.
这… 不可能
Made possible.
可你让这变可能了
By you in the House which you persuaded the Treasury to pay for.
就发生在那栋由你说服财政部来买单的房子里
Witchcraft's intelligence is genuine. It's been gold.
“巫术”的情报是确凿的，重要至极
It's just enough glitter amongst the chicken feed.
很小部分有价值罢了
Control didn't believe in miracles or in Witchcraft.
老总不相信什么奇迹或者巫术
But you were lazy and you were greedy,
但贪婪又懒惰的你们
and so you hounded him out of the Circus and you let Karla in.
把他挤出“马戏团”，将卡拉引狼入室
You opened negotiations to exchange intelligence with the Americans.
你们与美国佬协商交换情报
What they tell the Circus, they'll be telling the Kremlin.
美国佬告诉“马戏团”的，也会泄露给俄国
Witchcraft's information, the "gold" Karla let you have,
所谓“巫术”情报，不过是卡拉给你的垃圾情报
it wasn't to lure you.
不是在钓你
It was to lure the Americans.
而是在钓美国佬
Now,
现在
do you want to take credit for that?
你还觉得自己立了大功么？
What can we do?
我们该怎么做？
We have one thing the mole wants.
我们有一件“鼹鼠”想要的东西
- If I go to Paris...  - You'll go.
- 如果我去巴黎… - 你必须去
If I go to Paris,
如果我去巴黎
I want your word that you will get Irina back.
我要你保证你会把依瑞纳弄回来
I don't care who you have to trade. And I am out.
我不管你们用谁交易，我不管
I want a family, thank you. I do not want to end up like you lot.
我想要个安稳的家，谢谢，我可不想落下你们这样的下场
You will get her back.
你要把她弄回来
I'll do my utmost, Ricki.
我尽力，里基
Oh, hello, George.
你好，乔治
Hello.
你好
I want to talk about loyalty, Toby.
跟我谈谈忠诚吧，托比
Control recruited you, didn't he?
是老总将你招致麾下的，没错吧？
Found you starving in a museum in Vienna.
他在维也纳一个博物馆发现饥寒交迫的你
A wanted man.
还被通缉
Saved your life, I heard.
我听说，他救了你的命
And yet when the time came,
但在关键时刻
when it came to picking sides between him and Alleline,
要你在老总和阿勒莱恩之间做选择的时候
you didn't hesitate.
你毫不犹豫选择了阿勒莱恩
That's understandable, perhaps, with your war experience.
可以理解，可能是你的战争经历作祟
You survived this long, I suppose, because of your ability to change sides.
你能活这么久，我想是因为你那善于改换阵营的能力
Serve any master.
有奶就是娘
What? What's... What's this about, George?
这是怎么回事，什么状况，乔治？
It's about which master you've been serving, Toby.
关于你投靠哪边的主子，托比
Intelligence has been leaked, Toby.
情报在泄漏，托比
Someone's been taking files from the Circus.
有人在偷“马戏团”的内部资料
No, no, no, no. No.
不不不
This is a mistake, a misunderstanding.
这是个误会，误解
Files were delivered to a Russian attache, weren't they?
文件传递给了俄国专员，对不对？
Yes.
是的
And, yes, I delivered them.
是的，我传递的
But so did Percy Alleline.
但是珀西•阿勒莱恩也参与了
Good boy.
好狗
Bill Haydon.
比尔•海顿也有份
And so did Roy Bland.
罗伊•布兰德也有份
Things aren't always what they seem, George.
眼见不一定为实，乔治
You should know that.
你应该知道
Look, Moscow thinks Polyakov's...
俄方认为波利亚科夫…
working for them.
在为其效力
Every now and then we give him the odd file to take back to them.
我们时不时的给些没用的文件让他回去交差
Chicken feed, just to keep his bosses happy.
小部分有价值的也只是为了麻痹他的上司
But Polyakov's our Joe.
但波利亚科夫是我们的人
- He's a part of a big operation.  - Operation Witchcraft.
- 他是这项大行动的一分子 - “巫术”行动
Yes, I know.
我知道
George.
乔治
- Please, I don't deserve this.  - Who gave you the message
- 我不该被这样对待 - 谁让你捎信给吉姆•普里多
for Jim Prideaux to forget about Tinker, Tailor?
让其忘掉锅匠、裁缝这档子事的？
- Bland.  - To get rid of Connie Sachs?
- 布兰德 - 是谁炒掉康妮•萨克斯的呢？
- Westerby?  - Bland.
- 还有杰瑞•韦斯特比？ - 布兰德
Or Haydon.
或海顿
I don't know. One of them.
我不知道，但一定是他们其中之一
Or maybe Percy. No.
也可能是珀西
Well, I don't know who.
好吧，我不知道是谁
You're just the messenger.
你只是信使
Running between them all.
在他们之间跑腿
Anything to serve Witchcraft.
传递一切围绕巫术行动的情报
I know all about your secret source.
你知道的我都知道
And I know something you don't.
你不知道的，我也知道
I know who he is.
我知道谁是幕后人
He's Karla.
是卡拉
One of you has been giving Polyakov the crown jewels.
你们中有人给了波利亚科夫很重要的情报
- I did not know.  - Are you still a wanted man, Toby?
- 我不知道 - 你还是被通缉的人吧，托比？
- Look, George, I didn't know. I...  - You picked the wrong side.
- 听着，乔治，我不知道… - 你站错队了
No, you've got to believe me.
不，你得相信我
George, please.
乔治，求你
I am loyal.
我很忠诚
I... I am loyal.
我...我忠心耿耿
Don't... Don't... Don't send me back.
不要…不要把我送回去
Please, George.
求你，乔治
Don't send me back.
不要把我送回去
Give me the address.
给我那个地址
Where do you meet Polyakov?
你们在哪儿与波利亚科夫接头？
Hey, hey! Dog, dog, be quiet!
嘿嘿！狗狗，安静
What is this? Who are you?
这是做什么？你是谁？
- What are the safety signals?  - The air vent.
- 安全信号是什么？ - 排气孔
Open and all's well, closed and you're not to enter.
打开代表安全，关闭代表不便入内
And the microphone?
麦克风呢？
Peter?
彼得？
The boy stood on the burning deck whence all but he had fled;
男孩站在燃烧的甲板上/只有他逃了出来
The flame that lit the battle's wreck shone brightly o'er the dead.
火焰照亮了遍野的残骸/照亮了头顶的天际
Yet beautiful and bright he stood as born to rule the storm;
他勇敢且骄傲地昂首挺立/仿佛要控制整个风暴
A creature of heroic blood, a proud, though childlike form
鲜活的生灵/虽然是个孩子，但却骄傲地活着
The flames roll'd on...
火焰翻滚着…
Go on.
继续
The whole service is looking for you.
整个局里都在搜捕你
- They'll skin you alive if they find you.  - Maybe I want them to find me.
- 他们逮住你会活剥了你 - 也许我就想让他们发现我呢
You can go now. Leave the books and put the keys in the machines.
你可以走了，留下册子，把钥匙留在机器上
No, Ben stays here.
不，本你留下
Ricki Tarr claims to have information vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
里基•塔尔声称持有关于情报局内部安全的重要信息
Mr Smiley?
史迈利先生？
Taxi approaching Circus.
的士快到了“马戏团”了
Tinker.
“锅匠”
Tailor.
“裁缝”
Here comes Soldier.
这是“士兵”
Full house.
到齐了
- Well, go on then. Read it out loud.  - Personal for Tarr from Alleline.
- 大声读出来 - “阿勒莱恩给塔尔的私信
Require clarification before meeting your request.
“满足你的要求前需解释说明
Quote, information vital to safeguarding of the Circus, unquote
“引文，关系‘马戏团’安危的重要情报，结束引文…
does not qualify, send further information.
“太笼统，请发送具体情报”
Ah! That's it, Percy, you keep stalling.
哈，就这样，珀西，你继续拖吧
I warn you, Ben. We've got some really lousy people in this outfit.
我警告你，本，我们中间真的有内鬼
I wouldn't trust a fucking one of them.
我他妈谁都不信
The meeting's over.
会谈结束
They're leaving.
他们在离场
Craddox says I'll be off in a few days.
科拉道克斯说几天后就把我送走
I keep thinking how much I'm going to miss the cricket in Moscow.
我还在想自己在莫斯科会有多想念板球 （意指“马戏团”和俄国人做了某种交易，将放他回莫斯科）
I was rather hoping you might do a little light housekeeping for me.
我希望你能帮我打理点事
If I can.
尽量
There's a girl. Give her some money, would you?
有个姑娘，给她些钱，好吗？
And give her a good cover story.
编个故事
If it helps, tell her I love her.
如果能让她好过些，告诉她我爱她
It's all there.
就这么多
And there's a boy, too. Slip him a few quid to shut him up.
还有个男孩，给他点钱让他闭嘴
I know the inquisitors' bag of tricks. I taught most of them.
我知道审问官们的伎俩，大多是我教的
It's just a reaction.
不过是你来我往而已
An over-reaction, if you like.
或者说是逢场作戏也可
I did have one or two questions.
我的确还有一两个问题
- About Prideaux.  - Goddamn it!
- 关于普里多 - 天哪
- I got him back, didn't I?  - Yes, yes, you did.
- 是我把他救回来的，不是吗？ - 是的
That's good of you.
你办的好事
I am surprised Karla didn't have him shot.
我惊讶的是卡拉没把他毙了
Or do you think he held back,
或者你觉得他之所以没痛下杀手
out of delicacy towards you?
是为了照顾你的小情绪？
Did Prideaux come and see you before he left on the Hungarian mission?
普里多在去匈牙利前有没有见过你？
Yes, as a matter of fact he did.
事实上，见过
To say what?
说什么了？
To warn you.
他是去警告你吧
Because he knew deep down
因为他的直觉告诉他
it was you all along.
内奸一直都是你
So did you.
你也觉得是我吧
I had to pick a side, George.
我不得不选一边，乔治
It was an aesthetic choice as much as a moral one.
品位的选择多过于道德的选择
And the West has become so very ugly.
西方变得丑陋无比
Don't you think?
你不觉得吗？
Did Karla ever consider having you take over the Circus?
卡拉有没有考虑过让你接手“马戏团”？
I'm not his bloody office boy!
我又不是他该死的办公室小白脸！
What are you, then, Bill?
那你以为你是什么，比尔？
I'm someone who's made his mark.
我是个建功立业的人
Is there anything particular you want me to pass on to Ann?
有什么要我转告给安的吗？
Oh, that was nothing personal, George. I hope you understand that.
那不是针对你个人的，乔治，我希望你能理解
Karla said you were good,
卡拉说你是个厉害的角色
the one we had to worry about.
是我们重点防范的对象
But you do have a blind spot.
不过你确实还有一根软肋
He reckoned if I was known to be Ann's lover,
他推测如果我成了安人尽皆知的情人的话
you wouldn't be able to see me straight.
你反而不会那么容易看清我
And he was right.
事实证明他对了
Up to a point.
在一定程度上
I made this for you, sir.
先生，我帮你做了这个
I don't want you hanging around here any more.
我不想再见到你在这无所事事
Keep away from me from now on.
从今往后，离我远一点
- Go and join the others.  - But...
- 去加入其他同学们 - 可是…
Just... Just bloody join in, will you?
就...你就他妈的跟你的同学玩去，好吗？
Go and play, damn you!
去玩吧，真该死！
Could you check, Jerry?
你能去检查下么，杰瑞？